at any given time so at any given time
our dead experience there is always a
general well there's always a feeling
present but by that it's meant the quite
the general nature of the feeling that's
what it fundamentally determines how we
feel at a time at a particular time
often people confuse and tend to
conflate feelings with perceptions
whereby things that they can observe in
their body like sensations and various
sort of manifestations they think they
regard those things as feelings it's how
I feel this in my bad core that's that's
mistaken actually feelings are felt
perceptions of the seed so if there is
anything that you perceive or rather
there's anything any phenomenon
manifesting in your body on account of
your feelings well if it's in your body
its perceived on the level of the sense
of touch usually so feelings are always
felt that's why you can have more
particular feelings more general
feelings but doesn't matter wherever
your attention and ends up it's gonna be
that which is felt so you can have a
particular annoyance for example felt
unpleasantly but on a generator on a
more general level you are still
actually in a in a good mood so the more
general feeling that is simultaneously
present with this particular
unpleasantness that you might experience
through some annoyance the more the more
general feeling is is is enduring there
as such and you could you could call it
you could regard it as pleasant because
you're in a good mood
consequently you can sometimes be in a
unpleasant general feeling can be
present enduring it can be in a bad mood
loosely speaking and then even even the
most pleasing immediacy that you might
experience you feel agreeable will not
necessarily uproot you
moved because the the mind is the mind
is anchored in the general feeling that
this time it's unpleasant and it's
enduring on its own so no amount of
pleasant distractions in front of you
can take your mind away from it in that
sense on a particular level you are
experiencing agreeable feelings but on a
more general level a very disagreeable
mood still persists that's usually when
people turn to sensuality and
distraction because because trying to
try to over I try to bury that general
unpleasant feeling through through
engagement with immediate pleasure
that's whatever the sipping a person
doesn't know the escape from suffering
they are the first port of call II
sensuality they turn to sensuality
because they don't know any other means
of dealing with unpleasant feeling that
affects it but is receding well as I
spoke in many other videos and as you
can see in the suitors sensuality just
makes the problem worse because it makes
you ignore it ignore the problem pretend
there are no symptoms and issues while
the whole thing is just getting worse
because of that which means next time
you're affected by unpleasant feeling
you won't even necessarily need to
require a seriously unpleasant mood any
any displeasure will be enough to turn
you to sensuality because the mind is
becoming so weak and trying to get rid
of the discomfort at any cost as soon as
possible so that's what I mean by mood I
don't mean I go you're moody or I feel
like this so today I mean the general
feeling present so that's not I mean
it's um it's not a matter of what you
think your mood is it really matter
comes down to just checking looking
inwardly or backwardly or peripherally
and see what is the the general feeling
of the situation is it agreeable or
disagreeable or is it neutral
it can be either of that and that's what
mindfulness needs to needs to become
anchored and that's what it needs to
start to develop discernment
because that's the nature of the feeling
to be present in in the most general
manner and if we don't know escape from
it at that level if we are bound by the
dead level means it will be then
affecting our actions and at the
immediacy of our experience at the what
we call before the foreground at the
objects of your attention and that's
that's when people don't acknowledge
this don't are not aware of it they end
up sort of acting habitually either to
the sensuality or ill-will all on
account of being affected by the very
general feeling that they don't know
escape from so the most the costs
example would be for example when
somebody's in a bad mood over something
that they have no power over they
couldn't change it and then they go and
take it out on somebody else take out
their pain on somebody else and that
requires almost a metrical belief to
think that these two things are
connected that you can really alleviate
the pain and discomfort you feel in the
general level of mind that you can
alleviate that by kind of lashing out on
the particular level in the same sense
it requires a magical belief or a
gratuitous assumption to believe that
you can overcome that pain by replacing
with pleasure on a more particular level
the thing is particularly remains
particular and general remains general
which means you can invest all of your
attention and intention to the
particular sensuality and act
accordingly and trace it and get it and
and experience it but that makes no
difference to the nature of the general
feeling he might help you forget about
the nature of the general feeling and
then that general feeling will cease on
its own because that's what I do and
then you will believe that it ceased
because of your sensual act but actually
didn't all you need to do is just ask
yourself are you still liable to any
future unpleasant moods
and unpleasant states of mind on their
general level the answer will be yes
which means then sensuality doesn't do
anything cannot do anything to that
domain except distract you from the
problem so for as long as you resort to
looking away from the problem as a way
of solving the problem well you are
perpetuating the problem and making it
worse so that's why sensuality a new
will need to be restrained beforehand
and that also then means you limit the
scope of unwholesome actions that you
can still give into when you're affected
by the general mood because you want to
know the escape over night so the thing
is to recognize that but to know what
not to do on account of unpleasant
reason feelings then gradually the mind
will stop resorting to this quick sort
of distractions and look aways and
ignoring of this problem and it can well
it will leave itself no choice but to
look at it correctly and look at it
correctly it's basically if you stop
acting out of their general feeling and
practice mindful and sort and allow it
to endure for whatever it is no matter
how how many days it could last the bad
mood doesn't matter or a good mood that
doesn't matter either you allow it to be
without interfering without to try to
gather it trying to get rid of it and
then eventually you will have to see
that it has a reason on its own and
because of that it will cease on its own
because of that it cannot be yours
because its origin didn't come from you
thus you're not its creator you're not
its owner which means whatever has a
reason for that very reason it's
impermanent it cannot be honest it will change
and when that's fully understood then no
move no feeling no matter how general
that feeling is can affect the mind and
there is absolutely nothing and also
left there because the entire domain of
an all sonís was the result of ignorance
of not knowing where the problem was and
then trying to solve it or the
distracted from it by looking at the
wrong place and engaging with with wrong
things so once that problem has been
genuinely uprooted as we just explained
and well there is nothing nothing you
have to do an account